On November the 27th, 1942, the pride of
the French fleet sank in a matter of
hours in the port of Tulong.
It was not an enemy attack.  The French
sank their own ships.
The battleship Strasbourg the Cruisers
Colbert, Algeria and Duplex.  Over 85 of
the 173 ships in the harbor went down.
contradictions.  It forced its navy to
commit that most desperate of acts,
scutling its ships.
[music]
The scutling at Toulon was a direct
consequence of the debacle of the French
army.  The fur, satisfied with his rapid
victory, shared his intentions with
Mussolini to occupy France at a minimum
price and to handle the French army with
care so that some of them wouldn't take
up arms again.
It all hung on the signing of the armist
at Retond on June 22, 1940.
General Huner and Admiral Lucads,
they want to points.  France should be
able to keep an army, the empire and
remain in control of its fleet.
They still hoped they could negotiate
with Hitler.
Contrary to their expectations, no
negotiation was possible at Return.  The
arm disagreement imposed the division of
the territory and drastic conditions on
the French
thought saved the most important thing.
France could keep its army and
relieved its reported
India.
General Wine.  General Van.  Yes, my
general, if I have
my general, it's done.
Yes, General, it's
done.
specified that the Germans couldn't use
the French ships.  In return, they had to
be disarmed and placed under German
control.
This much coveted fleet was one of the
finest in the country's history.  It had
been entirely rebuilt since the 1920s.
On the eve of World War I, France's
colonial power was at its peak and the
fleet played a key role in bringing the
empire's farfung territories.
Under the colors that flew jindice
on the avenger, the French fleet
in 1939 brought together all the elements of a
naval force that is among the most
powerful in the world.
Despite its splendor, the fleet wasn't
able to prevent the debuck.
Even though it fought well, it fought
very little.
Other than in Navic alongside the
British.  And during the bombing of Genoa
in June 1940, the great French warships
weren't sent into battle.
And on board these ultra modern ships,
the organization and discipline remain
traditional.
Send.
We didn't have the right to vote at the
time.
It was forbidden.
We swore we would not
belong to any political party whatsoever
.   I, I did
the bugle calls on
the Strasbourg with the bugle in the
station where there was the
loudspeaker to announce many
things to the crew.
In the morning at 6am, the bar was shaken and the bugle sounded,
5 minutes after the march, the bugle sounded,
saying all the hammocks should be taken down,
5 minutes later at 6:10 we rang to
have breakfast, coffee
[music] [
music]
It didn't stop the clang from morning to night
and all the buildings were the same.
[music]
At the head of this fleet from 1937 was
François Darlon.
He was not liked in a large part
of the navy because he was a
politician, which is
relatively unappreciated in the maritime community,
but also because he had his own teams
.  We belonged to Darl's teams
where, at that time, we made a
career, or we didn't belong to them.
[music]
caught in a strangle hold between the
promise made and the armistice which put
most of the fleet under German control.
Darl found a way out.  He sent his
secret officer instructions to scutle
the ships.  He thought he found a way to
save face, but he had actually triggered
a time bomb.  France kept an unoccupied
zone protected by an army of 100,000
men.  It held on to its empire [music]
and the means of communicating with it,
its warships.  For the French military,
the war was over.
For the British, it continued.
Churchill, who no longer believed the
French, decided to neutralize the ships
within range before they went back to
France.  It was a catapult operation.
About 15 days later or maybe
3 weeks all the warships
well we were taken to Toulon or
Strasbourg to a cinema I think it
was the casino I think
to show us the Merced
Kir film.
We could really see the shell which is lying
in the dig
and then we saw the Bretagne when it
hit a block I think it
hit all the munition the boat it
was disoriented we
swam them in the sea we had to
leave for
the pairing too late
Froz
exploit angstruction
deberately point out that the British
offered admiral Jan three possibilities to scuttle the
ships, fight alongside the
British or rally a neutral port.
A few days later, the navy
[music] leads its dead to the
resting place.  The long fun procession, preceded by the
clergy [music], reaches the
Merel cemetery.  Men, whether admirals,
officers or sailors, simply mourn their loved ones;
we will remember Admiral Jeansoule before the
freshly opened graves
.
The chief finds the words to console
the seas.
The sailors, meanwhile [music] are searching
among the coffins for that of their
best comrade in arms.
I call on all French military personnel from the
army, navy and air force to come and join us
.  I invite all
young men and men of
tree-carrying age to enlist in this.
They must return to
British territory immediately.
regime warships arrived from to protect
on 23
came with
the whole world was deeply
outraged by the ignoble aggression committed
by the English on Dakar, an aggression
led by ex-General de Gaulle, traitor to
the fatherland, which failed thanks to the
heroic resistance of the French troops.  After
this revolting act, we finally received
the filmed report of the fighting that took place
.
[music]
and more closely with Germany
and Vishi sailors played a very
important role.
In 1941 Admiral Darlon was not only vice
president of the council but also
minister of foreign affairs.
Many admirals and the navy
were indeed very present
in the Vichi regime,
especially because it had not,
I would say, lost the war.
ed by the Germans.
The prisoners of war from the Navy were
all released.
Adolf Hitler agreed to suspend the arm's
agreement.  Key ships were assembled in
length and kept armed.
This new unit was known as the force of
high seas.
The elite of the French Navy was brought
together in the port.  But like the rest
of the Armistus Army, they didn't see
active service.
This served Hitler's interests because
meanwhile, in the Atlantic, a battle was
raging between Germanats and Britishs.
I was thoroughly questioned at the Pyrotheia
of Toulon.
And there were
maritime gendarmes guarding us,
and we were cleaning the shell casings,
and they were telling us, "Guys, you have to
enlist. Guys, you have to enlist.
You'll see, you'll see the colonies,
you can go to Africa."  And that's when it came to me getting
involved.
[music]
I was on board the Strasbourg
as a simple sailor and there we were
asked what you wanted to do
like that.  I said, well, I don't care,
but there are gunnery courses.
They enrolled me in a
gunnery course that lasted about 2 months.
Afterwards, they assigned me to a piece
of artillery.  He told me, "There you go, that's where
the fighting position is, you
come to that place."  So.
On board the ships, the sailors were
given training without knowing who the
real enemy was.
We were no longer at war.
We were no longer at war.  We have no
army left, nothing left.
And yes, there's more to Toulo than just the fleet.
We used to play a lot of cards and we
gambled away packs of cigarettes.  And that's where
I lost 800 cigarettes.
As soon as we went out in groups of 5000 or more, we were
entitled to campus freedom.  That
means the tobacco shop.
Each ship had its own orchestra, and
ours was just
hollow instruments.  For what ?  Because we used to
put packs of cigarettes in it on the
floor.  We would go downstairs and go to
the baker's or pastry shop to buy ourselves
a cake with cigarettes.
Yeah.  We were doing our little shopping.
So when we were at school, we had
permission for the day or
afternoon.
We were returning to Toulon.  Everything we were going to do
, we were in Toulon.  So.
We were proud of our outfit.   So.   So.
We used to see sailors in town that we don't
see anymore today.   So.
And I had opened the cinema.  They
went to the cinema from 10am until
10pm and when we went to the
cinema, we only saw
red pom-poms.  There were no civilians with
us.  He was just sailors.
And besides, there was the red-light district, which
no longer exists
.  Do you know what
the red-light district is?  The mess you guys
[laughs]
huh,
there was that.  So there were
often fights with the
mountain troops.
There were fights.
So we also patrolled, we
did the evening patrol, we
picked up the drunks and brought them
to the patrol car.
remained commander-inchief of the armed
forces.  The war was at a turning point.
After days and nights of fighting, the
free French forces won their first big
victory at Birakem.
The Germans were in difficulty on the
eastern front.  They were stuck in
Stalingrad.
And on the other side of the Atlantic,
the US joined the war.
When the Americans decided to land in
North Africa on November the 8th, 1942,
they didn't know what the attitude of
the French would be.
Mr. President, we are
fine, we don't want to
harm you.
We assure you that once the
threat from Germany and Italy
is well away from you, we
will leave your territory
immediately.
When we took the
American landing in Algiers
in Algeria we were satisfied happy we
said it starts there soon one
day it will be for
November
and
François happened to be present as he
was with his son who was
the Americans put pressure on him.  If
they managed to persuade the commander
chief of's forces to come over to their
side, the fighting would stop
immediately.  Darl wanted to be sure that
the landing was important enough to
alter the course of the war.
He also tried to gain the approval of
Vishi's military leaders who were just
as ward of the Germans as of the
British.  They thought France should ally
itself with the stronger side.
Some thought
even
wrong
days
French troops received contradictory
orders and stood up to the Americans.
In the fighting, over 1,300 French and
almost 500 Americans were killed.
On November 10th, Darles,
but he didn't want to give up the asset
of the fleet.
of the [music]
[music]
We had filled up on maout,
filled up on living supplies, the boat was ready to
sail.  all the ships of the squadron.
We've never been without oil, never.
We resupplied at BL, which was for
2 months at sea.
So, the ship's captain, Count Jean, was a
rather peculiar character who should
normally have been retired
when it happened. He was very
deeply affected by the
Merel Kebir affair and was a kind of
lord
with a lot of authority, and who, deep down, didn't accept much
dissent.
He was a legalist, in other words, there were
political leaders in Vichi who
gave the orders and he
executed them.
[music]
In 42,
French political leaders
and in particular many
French military personnel, especially the AMU, had
not yet grasped the magnitude of what
was happening, while
the Americans had entered the
war on the Eastern Front and were
encountering great
difficulties
in Russia.  Everything was
changing, and November 8th should have
enlightened them.
Mar
hit
French soldiers and air in the
previously unoccupied zone left their
camps and abandoned their weapons
without destroying
Thousands of vehicles, hundreds of
cannons, and over 1,00 planes were
seized by the occupying forces.  The
unoccupied zone and the French soldiers
who protected it were no more.  The army was
over.  The illusions of the armice hung.
The fleet could have left Toulon
within 24 or 48 hours of
the German invasion of the free zone
.  If he had wanted to
leave, they could have left, but there was
no desire to leave.
Admiral Marquis was the
maritime prefect of Toulon.  That is to say,
he was not at all responsible
for the fleet, he was responsible for
the supply of the fleet, the
security of the base and therefore of the
entrenched camp.  Marquy was the camp that had been cut off.
monitored and expelled.
With the Germans at the gates of Toulon,
the inevitable question was should they
stay or set?
All that remained of Ishi's crushed
dreams was the fleet isolated in the
harbor.
Marquis and Labord thought that they
could save their forces by giving Hitler
their word of honor that they wouldn't
fight against the Axis Alliance.
I found myself in the middle of the
sailors who were saying to the officers, we're
not going to stay here now, the Germans
have crossed the line, they're going to
come, they'd better leave and all that
.  A lot of guys were saying
Algeria, Algeria.  Among them were
many Ajacians, and the
Aljacians were afraid that if
the Germans came, they would be
conscripted into the German army.
We addressed our
respective leaders to say, "But we want to leave,
why are we waiting here? What are we
waiting for?"  So they came to us
, they consulted all the
senior officers, they said "We ca
n't leave,
we're here, we're waiting because we don't know what to
do."  So,
they refused to leave.
of the immediate
word of honor in particular circumstances
On all the boats, there was a
sabotage team that was planned but
also there were six good men who
were charged with planting the
explosives, blowing up the boat, finally
sinking it.  H, it
was during the night that we were called, either
during the night or at 9 pm perhaps, to
go and make the
preparations for scuttling the boat.
So naturally I didn't wear
the gas because that was what it
consisted of: putting firecrackers
on the hull and gas on top so that
the explosion would happen in the sea on the
seaward side, puncturing the hull.  But it was done
properly.  In other words,
we wanted the boat to sink straight down
.
We talked amongst ourselves.  We delegated the
quarter of Matchf
Henri, who was the oldest of the
torpedo boats, and Gravier, who was the
youngest of the gunner's mates,
to the inn, saying
that the entire crew, without exception, did
not want to scuttle themselves and, on the
contrary, wanted to continue the fight.
The answer was
rather evasive; it was not
categorical.  He said, "Don't worry
, trust me and obey."
And
in our opinion, in his mind, he had
already decided to leave.
Mediterranean.
They were ready to stand up to an allied
landing.  On November the 18th, the
Germans demanded that the last French
troop still remaining leave the
entrenched camp for a long time.  Around the
town, an increase in the German army's
activities was observed.  Despite that,
Marquis and Labard stuck to their guns.
For them, the threat could only come
from the sea, so all defenses were aimed
in that direction.
On November 26th, good evening, I was on
duty and as usual, we put the
rafts in place to allow the
passage of a so-called troop
and then at 9:10 am, we go to bed.
troops of the panzer and SS division
were already on their way to it was
called operation lila
at security post officer leert heard the
noise of armored vehicles.
It was 4:00.  They belonged to the
seventh Panzer division coming from the
west.
Leber tried to raise the alarm.  Seeing
that the lines were down, he decided to
send a police motorcyclist.
At the same time, the SS division Dasich
arrived from the east, passing the post
at Lavelette, 6 km from the town.
[music]
Wake up, I've come from Valletta.
The Germans are in Valletta.  The
pockets are there.
I came,
I saw
the Germans before they invaded the
arsenal; they had taken possession of
all the forts that overlooked the whole
area.
So all the anti-aircraft batteries,
and so on, had already been taken care of
by the Germans.
At 4:30, the Germans arrived at Foralg,
where Admiral Mary had set up his
headquarters as maritime chief of
police.
Hello !  Admiral Robin is online.  We need to
wake up Admiral La Borde.   Hurry
, the Germans are coming.
Around 5 a.m.,
we hear murmurs about
airline prices.
Oh !
And we thought I had a plane that was just passing through, flying
all the way.  Oh no, it was the
planes that dropped flares and it was
inside the building where I was, I
said we were going to get light
before 5am, the night was clear
.  It was good, it was better than we
expected.  Then we heard
gunshots, then we saw rockets, and
then there were more and more, and
then, and then, as I was saying,
we could barely breathe,
we were looking for fresh air.
[music]
He was told to wait until [music] 4:30
sharp before waking Laval and handing
him a letter, announcing that contrary
to his promises, the fur had given the
order to seize the fleet.
[music]
Laval, who knew of the secret scutling
orders, rushed to Vishi to stop the
catastrophe going ahead.
German,
is it [music]
that
Luke transmitted's order to avoid any
[music]
orders previously
had his
[music]
What do I tell them?
Authority
never [music]
any
of the crews.
[scream]
We were panicking, the microphones we were talking about
boarding, it was boarding, evacuated, evacuated, it was
boarding,
evacuated, and then it started to explode from
all sides.
There were the rioters.  So the
vandals break the wheels.  If the
Germans had boarded, they would have
closed the valves.  The boat
couldn't sink.
I went down to the machine and I was
ready.  I had my blowtorch in my hand and
I was ready to give the reducer a good whack with the blowtorch
.  An abominable thing.  Well
done,
we ordered the flooding of the holds
because as there is a lot of
ammunition and powder in the holds,
we simply pressed a
button and the boat sank very
slowly.
So, don't stop
p it lasted for 3 days day and
night without stopping
and as the weather was overcast
that day, he wanted to see the smoke
because the boats were catching fire.
There was also some maize that caught fire, it
was impossible.
And then we saw panzers
coming towards the main gate,
driving at a fairly high speed, and
when they arrived in front of the
return
to make a stop, that's when
we started firing a
little, but it didn't last long because
all the boats jumped and boarded,
and that was the end of the battle.
Le Mouran,
a submarine, is like a car.
You press the starter button, it starts.
We don't need to heat it beforehand.
When we left the platform, the
Germans shot at us.  with machine guns
they were
30m from us we saw them, they
were there we were
the
first to present ourselves at the place of Saintendrier
closed by nets operated by a tug
which did not want to
open for us because there was no superior order
B the commander II went all the way
to the bow touched the
tug saying the superior orders
there I give them to you.
And we, we went through just enough
to get through and we dove in.
Then we could hear the ears of
mines scraping the hull.  We
expected it to blow up any
second now, and it did.
We see the door coming, opening,
German,
helmet pushed down to his forehead,
machine gun in hand,
he has bands of bands, machine gun,
grenades, crossed
hands.
not in the air
said Raust the last one he makes the entrance
Raust Raust vi outside
we took what we could and there were
already soldiers who were on
the platform soldiers and who were trying to
climb but they did not climb they could
not climb yet.  We were the ones who went
down.  We went downstairs, where there were able-
bodied people, with all sorts of stuff.  We were able to go
downstairs and as we went along
he made us line up against a wall.
I found myself with a comrade
in the arsenal.  We could hear the
sound of explosions from all the boats being blown up
and we didn't move.  We
were there waiting for the end of
all this reorganization that had taken place.
We could see the boats as we passed by, we could
see the boats that were
half sunk, the flags that were
touching the water.  It breaks your heart.
What did they do to us to make us go out
to the Castignho gate?
At the Cast gate,
I was able to give a
draft of paper to a person
who was there and who
sent to my parents that I was in
good health, that what remained of me was
the vulture ribbon.
What will become of us?  Everyone
is asking the question.  Uh, the
Germans brought us back to the depot,
what are we going to do with us?  That's where we
learned from the officers who
were in the depot that we were going to be
put on leave to go home
.
still believed in the idea of ​​neutrality
and refused to join the allies.
We are aware that we have
disobeyed.  We disobeyed not
the government, but we disobeyed
Pétin, Val, in short, the whole
government.  So we were
rebels.
This hero
bed by de created a legend for himself
which for years overshadowed the other
protagonists of the scuting those who
obeyed orders.
One can refuse to carry out an order that
is contrary to the laws of war,
that is contrary
to human rights.
The first thing you can do is
resign, say "Listen to
me, I won't do that."
Well, after the decision to disobey,
and disobey, it implies for
military leaders that you are able to
impose your decision on
those under your orders to make them make
a different decision.  Well, that's always a case-by-
case situation, but at that point,
you get out of that,
I would say, legal relationship between
political power and
military responsibility.  And at that point, well,
history will judge whether you were
right
or wrong.
At the moment when our ships were about to be
seized by the enemy, the national reflex kicked in, with the
crews and
staffs taking up arms.
France heard the cannon of Toulon.
was at losing fleet in his memoir he
said he was overcome with anger and
sorrow at this tragedy
after the war the admirals were judged
very severely by the high courmiral
de la was sentenced to death in 1947
at his trial he declared I was only ever
pro France
Admiral sentenced force laboral
and admiral mary sentenced
officers
in de 192.
Ga
for officers of the [music] army.
Jean de became a French resistance
fighter whereas until 1942 was a
general in Vish's army.
The Vishi sailors lost their ships
[music] and despite their efforts they
were excluded from the great liberation
saga.
For the navy the scuting of the fleet
became subject.   It gave me
chills.
I felt a shiver run through me.  I
said, but we're not going to do that.
I'm not going to do that.
What do you want us to say when we're
20?
We were just following orders, that's
all.   Do
n't try to understand.  We were told
to do this, so we did that.  It was good
or it wasn't good.
Then the boat has a soul.  I had
stayed on the boat for 5 years, well, I loved
my boat
and I didn't want to scuttle it.
It's a bit of a relief to
tell you this because
sometimes it's a burden to say you
did abominable things or I didn't do
anything
abominable because what I was
supposed to do I didn't do.
We cried.
Yes,
because we didn't see it,
but even we inside could
hear the explosions,
and I'm telling you, there were still 85
boats that exploded in Toulon.  So,
it was making noise
and at that moment,
we cried like children.
Yes yes.
[music]